the predictor that fixes the two
mispredictions paranormally behavior of
the one bit predictor is called a
two-bit predictor often we write that as
2bp or even a
2bc which stands for a 2bit counter we
will see that this predictor behaves
like a two bit counter the two bit
predictor has possible value 0 0 0 1 1 0
and 1 1 the way it works is that the
more significant bit of the predictor
tells us what the prediction should be
so this is what we will call the
prediction bit the more significant bit
of this predictor this prediction bit
really functions similarly to how the
one bit predictor functions this lower
bit here is called the hysteresis or
conviction bit this bit tells us how
sure are we that we should be predicting
what the prediction bit is saying
usually
the state 0 0 is treated as a strong not
taken State this means that we will be
predicting not taken and we are fairly
convinced that not taken is the dominant
behavior of this Branch the 01 state
will be the weak not taken prediction
State we are still going to predict not
taken but this time we are less sure
that that's the dominant Behavior
similarly here for the predict taken
States we have weak taken and a strong
taken state so how does this predictor
work the one bit predictor only had the
not taken and the taken state if our
state is zero we will predict not taken
if we indeed see the not taken decision
later we stay in this state next time we
will predict not taken to if however we
are predicting not taken but the
decision turns out to be taken we change
our mind and move to the taken state in
the taken State we stay there if the
branch is indeed taken but if we predict
taken and see that the branch is not
taken we go back to the not taken State
and start predicting that so pretty much
one outcome changes our mind completely
about what to do with the branch and
that has resulted in two mispredictions
per anomaly let's say that the dominant
behavior is not taken the first time the
branch is seen to be taken we move here
and then the branch moves back to the
dominant Behavior we will predict taken
and mispredict again before we move here
with the two bit predictor we have four
states 0 0 01 1 0 and 1 one now this is
our strong not taken State and of course
if we see a not- taken decision we stay
there we were convinced that the branch
will be not taken and the outcome really
confirms that if we see a single taken
decision from the strong not taken State
we move to the weak not taken so now we
are predicting that the branch is still
not taken but we are less convinced
about that in the case when the non-t
taken behavior is the dominant one this
would be the anomaly and we would move
back to the strong not taken State once
we see that the branch is not taken so
the idea is that unlike here where the
anomaly itself will result in a
misprediction and then we would predict
differently so the dominant Behavior
would be again mispredicted for once
here this taken while in the strong not
taken state will be a misprediction but
then we will predict not taken it's just
a weak prediction so we would be right
for this not taken outcome so if the
branch really is mostly not taken we
only have a misprediction when the
anomaly happens not also when the
dominant Behavior happens after the
anomal similarly if we are in the strong
taken State We Believe now that the
taken behavior is the dominant one a
single not taken will result in a
misprediction but move us to a weak
taken state so that if we see a taken
outcome again we don't mispredict and we
move back to the strong taken state of
course we stay in the strong taken State
as long as we are seeing the taken
outcome so the idea is that if not taken
is a dominant Behavior we expect the
predictor to stay in these two states if
taken is the dominant Behavior we expect
the predictor to stay in these two
states
either way it's predicting so that only
the anomaly gets mispredicted but not
the dominant behavior that follows the
anomaly however we can have a branch
that for example tends to be not taken
for a while and then changes its mind
about it and starts being taken for a
while thus if we are in the weak taken
State and we see another taken
outcome we will go to one of the taken
States and similarly if we are in the
weak taken state and we see another not
taken we will move to the one of the not
taken States so the idea is that if we
see a branch it is mostly not taken
periodically it's may be taken and then
again stays not taken we stay in these
two states and keep predicting not taken
but if the branch starts being taken
very often from now on it will take one
two mispredictions before we are in the
taken States and start predicting taken
again so somehow a single anomaly will
cost us one
misprediction a switch in Behavior will
cost us two
mispredictions so why we call this a 2
bit counter is because if you look at
what this is doing is it's a counter
that counts up when the branch is taken
and saturates at three and counts down
when it's not taken and saturates at
zero so really it's a two bit counter
that just counts up when the branch is
taken and counts down as the branch is
not taken this also means that this is a
relatively easy Behavior to implement
basically it's very easy to implement
this type of predictor